ALL CHARACTERS, ORGANIZATIONS, EVENTS, AND LOCATIONS IN THIS SHOW ARE FICTITIOUS
모든 캐릭터, 조직, 이벤트, 이 쇼의 위치는 허구입니다.
We have ROSC. Check his vitals, please.
우리에겐 ROSC가 있습니다. 바이탈을 확인해 주세요.
Dr. Cha!
차 박사님!
Open your eyes!
눈을 뜨세요!
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Dr. Cha!
차 박사님!
What happened to her?
그녀에게 무슨 일이 일어났나요?
She was electrocuted after touching the patient's body during CPR.
그녀는 만진 후 감전사했다 CPR 중 환자의 신체.
Jeez, she's such a klutz.
이런, 그녀는 정말 멍청해요.
What?
무엇?
You're awake.
당신은 깨어있습니다.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
Why am I here?
내가 왜 여기에 있는 걸까요?
Do you not remember?
기억나지 않나요?
You fainted after you were electrocuted during CPR.
당신은 기절했습니다 CPR 도중 감전된 후.
Me?
나?
I did?
내가 그랬어?
You made a mistake that not even med students make.
당신은 실수를 했어요 의대생도 만들지 않는 것입니다.
You created a moment that'll go down in our hospital's history.
당신은 순간을 창조했습니다 그건 우리 병원 역사에 남을 거예요.
Anyway, I think you've laid down enough, so why don't you get up now?
어쨌든, 충분히 누워 계셨다고 생각해요. 그럼 이제 일어나면 어때?
Okay. I'm sorry.
좋아요. 죄송합니다.
Why on earth did you do that?
도대체 왜 그랬나요?
I don't know.
모르겠습니다.
I must've been distracted.
제가 정신이 산만해졌나 봐요.
Jeez, this is embarrassing.
이런, 이거 부끄럽다.
That's not the issue.
그게 문제가 아니예요.
Do you know how shocked I was? I mean, earlier…
내가 얼마나 충격받았는지 알아? 내 말은, 더 일찍…
Father was in the ER at the time,
당시 아버지는 응급실에 계셨고,
and he screamed at everyone and carried you all the way here.
그리고 그는 모두에게 소리를 질렀어요 그리고 당신을 여기까지 데려다줬어요.
I've never seen him so flustered like that.
나는 그를 본 적이 없다 너무 당황해서.
Everyone, out of the way!
다들 비켜!
No!
아니요!
Your dad did?
너희 아버지가 그랬어?
Check up on your mom's condition often and look out for her.
엄마의 상태를 자주 확인하세요 그리고 그녀를 조심하세요.
It might be hard, but I trust that you'll understand my position.
힘들겠지만, 난 믿어요 내 입장을 이해해줄 거라고.
Keep up the good work.
계속해서 좋은 일을 하세요.
I'm the one who's doing all the work.
나는 모든 일을 하는 사람이다.
Why did I…
내가 왜…
What happened to her?
그녀에게 무슨 일이 일어났나요?
She was electrocuted after touching the patient's body during CPR.
그녀는 만진 후 감전사했다 CPR 중 환자의 신체.
Jeez, she's such a klutz.
이런, 그녀는 정말 멍청해요.
You have a sense of humanity that I lack.
당신은 나에게 부족한 인간미를 갖고 있어요.
That's if I were to put it nicely. To be blunt, you're just nosy.
내가 그것을 멋지게 표현한다면 말이다. 무뚝뚝하게 말하자면, 당신은 참견이 심한 사람일 뿐입니다.
Anyway,
어쨌든,
I let you date me because of that quality of yours.
데이트하자고 했어 당신의 그 품질 때문입니다.
But I've been feeling off recently.
그런데 최근 기분이 안 좋아졌어요.
Don't you think you're a bit too friendly with that lady?
당신은 생각하지 않는가? 너 그 여자랑 좀 너무 친해?
-Me? -Yes.
-나? -예.
I'm having trouble putting a name to this feeling.
문제가 발생했습니다 이 느낌에 이름을 붙이는 것.
Jealousy?
질투?
That's a gross way to put it.
그것은 그것을 표현하는 거친 방법입니다.
Camaraderie…
동지애…
is a rather contemptible way to describe it.
다소 경멸적인 방법이다 그것을 설명하기 위해.
The word jealousy grosses me out as well.
질투라는 단어도 나에게 역겹다.
It's nothing. It's just…
그것은 아무것도 아니다. 그것은 단지…
Let's just go with camaraderie.
그냥 동지애로 가자.
That word doesn't cut it.
그 말은 잘리지 않습니다.
Let's just call it pity.
그냥 불쌍하다고 부르자.
Whatever. Think what you want.
무엇이든. 당신이 원하는 것을 생각하십시오.
More importantly,
더 중요한 것은,
you "let me date you"?
당신은 "나 데이트하자"?
"Let me"?
"내가"?
I know I liked you first, but isn't this some kind of power trip?
내가 먼저 당신을 좋아했다는 걸 알아요 하지만 이건 일종의 권력 여행이 아닌가?
You didn't know?
몰랐어요?
There are power dynamics in romantic relationships.
힘의 역학이 있습니다 낭만적인 관계에서.
You like me more, so I have power over you.
당신은 나를 더 좋아하고, 그래서 나는 당신에 대한 권한을 가지고 있습니다.
Well…
음…
Ma'am.
부인.
You're here.
당신은 여기 있습니다.
I'm not too knowledgeable about art schools,
나는 지식이 너무 부족하다 미술학교에 대해서,
so I'm not sure exactly how to help you.
그래서 나는 당신을 어떻게 도와야할지 정확히 모르겠습니다.
Does your mother have any strategies to support you?
당신의 어머니는 가지고 계십니까? 당신을 지원할 전략이 있나요?
My mom?
우리 엄마?
When you were preparing for med school,
의과대학을 준비하던 시절,
she was knowledgeable enough to be a college counselor.
그녀는 충분히 지식이 있었어 대학 상담사가 되는 것.
She doesn't know much about preparing for art school admissions.
그 사람은 아는 게 별로 없어 미술대학 입시 준비에 대해.
And right now,
그리고 바로 지금,
she's busy pursuing her own career.
그녀는 자신의 경력을 쌓느라 바쁘다.
Excuse me, Professor.
죄송합니다, 교수님.
You have something stuck in your hair.
당신의 머리카락에 뭔가가 붙어 있습니다.
Here.
여기.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Hey, daughter.
안녕, 딸.
Is something the matter?
뭔가 문제가 있나요?
Was I hallucinating?
내가 환각을 느꼈던 걸까?
"Daughter"?
"딸"?
She has a daughter?
그녀에게 딸이 있나요?
The surgical site is healing well.
수술 부위는 잘 아물고 있습니다.
I think you'll be able to be discharged this week.
내 생각엔 당신이 할 수 있을 것 같아요 이번 주에 퇴원 예정이다.
-Goodness. Thank you, Doctor. -It's nothing.
-선량. 고마워요, 박사님. - 아무것도 아니에요.
-Then I'll see you on my rounds tomorrow. -Please wait one moment.
-그럼 내일 라운드에서 뵙겠습니다. - 잠시만 기다려주세요.
Here.
여기.
I made this from the apples we raise ourselves.
내가 이걸 만들었어 우리가 직접 키운 사과에서.
Please have some together.
함께 드시기 바랍니다.
-Thank you. -Yes.
-감사합니다. -예.
Isn't that crazy?
그거 미친거 아니야?
Here, a present.
여기, 선물이에요.
This apple juice purely consists of apples raised with love and care.
이 사과 주스는 순수하게 구성되어 있습니다. 사랑과 보살핌으로 자란 사과.
This is precious stuff, so be sure to savor every drop.
소중한 물건이군요, 그러니 한 방울 한 방울도 꼭 맛보세요.
-Thank you.
-감사합니다.
But what was so funny?
그런데 뭐가 그렇게 재밌었어?
Professor, you remember that older resident right?
교수님, 기억나시나요? 그 나이든 주민 맞죠?
The one who asked you for a ride after the dinner party.
태워달라고 하신 분이 만찬 후에.
-Dr. Cha Jeong-suk? -Yes.
-박사. 차정숙? -예.
Apparently, she got electrocuted today after touching her patient during CPR.
아무래도 오늘 감전된 것 같군요. 심폐소생술 중 환자를 만진 후.
Isn't that wild?
그건 야생 아닌가요?
What's her condition? Is she okay?
그녀의 상태는 어떻습니까? 그 사람 괜찮아요?
She didn't get hurt?
그 사람은 다치지 않았나요?
Yes, they said she went right back to work.
응, 그녀가 갔다고 했어 바로 직장으로 돌아갑니다.
Besides, first-year residents have to act like they're fine
게다가 1년차 입주자 괜찮은 것처럼 행동해야 해
even if they actually aren't.
실제로는 그렇지 않더라도 말이죠.
That's a relief.
다행이네요.
But is that something to laugh about?
그런데 그게 웃을 일인가요?
DR. CHA, I HEARD WHAT HAPPENED…
박사. 차, 무슨 일이 있었는지 들었어…
You're going to get the surgery?
수술을 받으러 가시나요?
Yes.
예.
-You're not going to go to the US? -I don't want to go.
- 미국에는 안 갈 거예요? -가고 싶지 않아요.
I'm going to get the surgery here.
여기서 수술을 하려고 합니다.
I'm counting on you.
나는 당신을 믿고 있습니다.
Even though I'm not in a position where I can do much for your surgery,
내가 처한 상황이 아니더라도 내가 당신의 수술을 위해 많은 것을 할 수 있는 곳,
I must say you really made the right decision, Chairman Oh.
정말 만들었다고 해야 할까요 올바른 결정이었습니다, 오회장님.
We'll do our best.
최선을 다하겠습니다.
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
You fainted while trying to save me.
당신은 나를 구하려다 기절했습니다.
Who told you that?
누가 그런 말을 했나요?
I saw it.
나는 그것을 보았다.
But you were in cardiac arrest then.
그런데 그때 당신은 심장마비 상태였어요.
Well, I experienced something rather odd
음, 좀 이상한 일을 겪었어요
that I never thought I'd come across in my life.
내가 생각해본 적도 없는 일이야 나는 내 인생에서 우연히 만날 것입니다.
He went on and on about wanting to be discharged.
그는 계속해서 갔다 퇴원하고 싶다는 얘기.
He's a nuisance to the very end.
끝까지 귀찮은 놈이에요.
Who said he wasn't?
누가 아니라고 했어?
I guess he won't be able to go to the US like he wanted.
그 사람은 못할 것 같아 그가 원하는 대로 미국에 가기 위해.
He just suddenly collapsed.
그는 갑자기 쓰러졌습니다.
Do you think I forgot Eun-bi's birthday?
내가 은비 생일을 잊어버린 것 같니?
Then what do you expect me to do?
그러면 내가 무엇을 하기를 바라나요?
You want me to leave that old geezer?
내가 그 늙은 괴짜를 떠나길 바라나요?
He's going to kill me.
그는 나를 죽일 것입니다.
Can you just let it…
그냥 놔둬도 되나요…
It's just this once. It's not as if this happens all the time!
딱 이번 한 번이에요. 이런 일이 항상 일어나는 것은 아닙니다!
Come on!
어서 해봐요!
"Old geezer"?
"늙은 괴짜"?
The weather just had to be great today.
오늘은 날씨가 좋을 수밖에 없었습니다.
I should be golfing on a day like this!
이런 날엔 골프를 쳐야지!
Are you not worried about your father?
아버지 걱정은 안 하시나요?
That condescending old man is called "the phoenix" for a reason.
저 뻔뻔한 노인네 이유 때문에 "피닉스"라고 불립니다.
He'll probably come back like a phoenix this time too.
그 사람 아마 돌아올 거야 이번에도 피닉스처럼.
He cares about his money too much to just leave like this.
그 사람은 돈에 너무 신경을 써요 그냥 이대로 떠나려고.
Aren't you secretly hoping that he passes away?
몰래 바라고 있지 않나요 그 사람이 세상을 떠났다고?
Hey, what do you take me for?
이봐, 나를 뭘로 생각하는 거야?
What would the need for that be?
그럴 필요는 무엇입니까?
In the end, everything will be mine anyway.
결국, 어쨌든 모든 것은 내 것이 될 것입니다.
You worthless bastard!
이 쓸모없는 놈아!
You little bastard.
이 작은 놈.
Where is he?
그는 어디에 있나요?
Charge it to 200J.
200J까지 충전하세요.
One, two, administering shock.
하나, 둘, 충격을 가하는 거죠.
I don't know if I should say that I experienced the afterlife,
말해야 할지 모르겠습니다 사후 세계를 경험했다는 사실을요.
or that I had an out-of-body experience.
또는 유체이탈 체험을 했다고 합니다.
Anyway,
어쨌든,
experiencing death made me realize
죽음을 경험하면서 깨달았다
that I needed to live.
내가 살아야 한다는 걸.
No matter how crappy life might be, living is always better than dying.
인생이 아무리 형편없더라도, 사는 것이 죽는 것보다 항상 낫습니다.
If I die, it's only a loss for me.
내가 죽으면 그것은 나에게만 손해일 뿐입니다.
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
Set a date for my surgery.
수술 날짜를 정해주세요.
Yes, Chairman Oh.
네, 오회장님.
I understand, as someone who was on the brink of death as well.
이해해요, 누군가로서 그것도 죽음의 문턱에 있던 사람.
You should survive until the very end and do everything you want.
끝까지 살아남아야 해 그리고 당신이 원하는 모든 것을하십시오.
-So you won't have any regrets. -Shall I?
-그래서 후회는 없을 거예요. -그럴까요?
-My goodness. Are you alright? -I'm fine.
-이럴 수가. 괜찮으세요? -잘 지내요.
Jeez, you startled me. Chairman Oh, you have to be careful.
이런, 당신은 나를 놀라게 했어요. 아 회장님 조심하셔야 합니다.
I'm fine.
잘 지내요.
I have two problematic patients, you know?
제겐 문제가 있는 환자가 두 명 있어요. 아시죠?
Because they keep telling me that they don't want to get treated.
계속 나한테 말하니까 치료받기를 원하지 않는다는 것입니다.
But among the two, one of them told me today that he will get his surgery.
그런데 그 둘 중에 한 분이 나한테 말하더군요. 오늘 그는 수술을 받을 것이다.
You can't imagine how hard he cried when he heard about his condition.
그 사람이 얼마나 울었는지 넌 상상도 못 할 거야 그의 상태를 들었을 때.
I felt so terrible.
나는 너무 끔찍하다고 느꼈습니다.
It's such a relief now.
이제 정말 안심이 됩니다.
When I first learned of my condition,
내 상태를 처음 알았을 때,
I cried too.
나도 울었다.
Because I was so thankful.
너무나 감사했기 때문입니다.
It was like a gift to me…
나에게 주는 선물 같았어요...
since I didn't have the courage to kill myself.
내가 없었기 때문에 자살할 수 있는 용기.
I had the guts to take someone else's life,
나는 배짱이 있었다 다른 사람의 생명을 앗아가는 것,
but I didn't have the nerve to take my own.
하지만 난 없었어 내 것을 가져갈 용기.
You said you don't have the nerve,
용기가 없다고 하셨는데,
but how were you able to do that to someone else?
그런데 어떻게 할 수 있었어? 그게 다른 사람한테?
-Doctor. -Yes?
-의사. -예?
Could you please prescribe me some cold medicine?
저에게 처방해 주실 수 있나요? 감기약 좀?
Are you sick?
당신은 아픈가요?
I'm aching all over.
온몸이 아프다
A family member of the corrections officer for the next shift passed away.
교정관의 가족 다음 교대 근무가 사망했습니다.
Goodness, it's going to be hard to prescribe medicine in the ward.
맙소사, 힘들겠다 병동에서 약을 처방합니다.
But I'll try to go find some medicine.
하지만 약을 좀 찾아봐야겠습니다.
DR. CHA, I HEARD WHAT HAPPENED, ARE YOU…
박사. 차, 무슨 일이 있었는지 들었어 당신은…
Professor!
교수님!
What brings you here?
무슨 일로 여기까지 왔나요?
I thought Chief Resident Hwang might be here.
황 실장 생각했어요 여기에 있을 수도 있습니다.
She's not here right now. Is she not answering her phone?
그녀는 지금 여기 없습니다. 그 사람이 전화를 안 받나요?
I'll try calling her.
그 사람에게 전화해 볼게요.
Okay, then I'll get going now.
알았어, 그럼 이제 가볼게.
She seems fine.
그녀는 괜찮아 보인다.
Mom.
엄마.
I need to talk to you.
얘기 좀 해야겠어요
-Right now? -Yes, right now.
-지금 바로? -네, 지금 당장요.
Okay.
좋아요.
The art academy instructors can only do so much for my art project report.
미술학원강사는 할 수 있는 일만 내 예술 프로젝트 보고서에 이만큼이요.
It's critical for early admissions, but it's beyond my ability to do it alone.
조기입학이 중요해요 하지만 혼자서 그것을 하는 것은 내 능력 밖이다.
I looked into it,
살펴보니,
and there are consultants that specialize in art school--
컨설턴트도 있고 미술 학교를 전문으로 하는 곳입니다.
Mom!
엄마!
Did I nod off?
내가 고개를 끄덕였나요?
I'm sorry. I'm just so tired these days.
죄송합니다. 요즘 너무 피곤해요.
Where did we leave off?
우리는 어디에서 떠났습니까?
Forget it. Why bother when you're not even interested in me?
잊어버리세요. 왜 귀찮게? 나한테 관심도 없을 때?
Come on, it's not like that.
어서, 그런 것이 아닙니다.
Why would I have no interest in you?
내가 왜 너한테 관심이 없지?
Then are you aware I had a consultation with my homeroom teacher today?
그럼 내가 상담을 했다는 걸 알고 있니? 오늘 담임 선생님이랑 같이?
I've just been so out of it these days.
요즘 너무 정신이 없었어요.
I-rang,
아이링,
I went through a lot today, okay?
나 오늘 정말 많은 일을 겪었어, 알았지?
I'll explain--
설명할게요--
I don't need your explanation.
당신의 설명은 필요하지 않습니다.
Let's just live our lives separately from now on.
그냥 우리 인생을 살자 지금부터 따로.
That's what you'll prefer anyway.
어쨌든 당신이 선호하는 것이 바로 그것이다.
I-rang.
아이링.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
You startled me.
당신은 나를 놀라게 했습니다.
Are you asleep?
당신은 자고 있습니까?
No.
아니요.
But why are you like that?
그런데 왜 그러세요?
Did something bad happen?
뭔가 나쁜 일이 있었나요?
No.
아니요.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
What?
무엇?
Come here.
이리 오세요.
Why?
왜?
Stop talking back and just come over here.
말대꾸는 그만하고 여기로 오세요.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Is it my birthday present?
내 생일 선물인가요?
That bracelet?
그 팔찌?
It's so pretty.
너무 예뻐요.
Honey, it's so pretty.
여보, 너무 예뻐요.
Give it to me.
나에게 주세요.
It's beautiful.
아름답습니다.
I'm glad to hear you like it.
마음에 든다니 기쁘네요.
I'll cherish this forever.
나는 이것을 영원히 소중히 여길 것이다.
Thank you, honey.
고마워요, 여보.
Come on, don't go overboard. I can just buy you another one.
어서, 너무 멀리 가지 마세요. 그냥 하나 더 사줄 수 있어요.
This is the first present I've received from you.
이게 첫 번째 선물이야 나는 당신에게서 받았습니다.
So it's that much more meaningful.
그래서 더욱 의미가 깊습니다.
First?
첫 번째?
Makes you think you've been too neglectful, doesn't it?
당신이 그랬다고 생각하게 만드네요 너무 소홀하지 않나요?
And about I-rang.
그리고 아이랑에 대해서.
It seems like she's being rebellious, which is unlike her.
아무래도 반항적인 것 같긴 한데, 그녀와는 다릅니다.
It's all my fault.
다 내 잘못이에요.
She's in 12th grade. I should have taken better care of her.
그녀는 12학년이에요. 나는 그녀를 더 잘 보살펴야 했어요.
How about
어때?
you delay your residency for a year
1년 동안 거주를 연기하는 경우
until I-rang gets into med school?
아이랑이 의과대학에 들어갈 때까지?
If you still haven't changed your mind after I-rang gets into med school,
아직도 마음이 변하지 않았다면 아이랑이 의과대학에 입학한 후,
it won't be late to start then.
그때 시작해도 늦지 않을 거예요.
I do feel bad about I-rang.
나는 아이랑에 대해 기분이 나쁘다.
Of course you do.
물론 그렇습니다.
Her mother turned a blind eye to her at such an important time in her life,
그녀의 어머니는 그녀에게 눈을 감았다. 그녀의 인생에서 매우 중요한 시기에,
which resulted in her feeling isolated and rebellious.
그 결과 그녀는 이렇게 느꼈다. 고립되고 반항적이다.
How much pain she must be in, right?
그 사람은 얼마나 고통스러울까요?
I think I might have taken
아마 내가 가져갔을 것 같아
the kids' problems too lightly.
아이들의 문제를 너무 가볍게 본다.
By the way, honey,
그건 그렇고, 자기야,
I think Seung-hi has a daughter too.
승희에게도 딸이 있는 것 같아요.
Really?
정말?
Eat up.
먹어라.
Do you feel good about stuffing your faces by yourselves?
기분이 좋나요? 혼자서 얼굴을 채우는 것에 대해?
What? Damn it!
무엇? 젠장!
What? You are worthless!
무엇? 당신은 쓸모가 없습니다!
GUSAN UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL DEPOSIT 3,260,000 WON
구산대학교병원 보증금 3,260,000원
MOM
엄마
Mom, is there anything you want?
엄마, 갖고 싶은 거 있어요?
Why are you suddenly asking me about what I want?
갑자기 왜 나한테 묻는 거야? 내가 원하는 것에 대해?
Mom, I got paid today.
엄마, 나 오늘 월급 받았어요.
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원하세요?
Wait, would cash be better?
잠깐, 현금이 더 좋을까요?
I don't need anything. Just spend it on yourself.
나는 아무것도 필요하지 않습니다. 그냥 자신에게 쓰세요.
You can splurge.
당신은 과시 할 수 있습니다.
Goodness, it's not enough to splurge.
맙소사, 과시하는 것만으로는 충분하지 않습니다.
TRANSFER 500,000 WON TO OH DEOK-RYE
50만원 이체 오덕례에게
500,000 WON TRANSFERRED
500,000원 이체됨
UNDERWEAR 3 SET 89,900 WON
속옷 3세트 89,900원
YOUR PURCHASE IS COMPLETE!
구매가 완료되었습니다!
Have a good day.
좋은 하루 보내세요.
BOOK OF PAINTINGS BY MUNCH
뭉크의 그림책
YOUR PURCHASE IS COMPLETE!
구매가 완료되었습니다!
NECKTIES FOR MEN
남성용 넥타이
PRODUCT DETAILS FOR 1ST WINTER NECKTIE_10
제품 세부정보 첫 번째 겨울 넥타이_10
YOUR PURCHASE IS COMPLETE!
구매가 완료되었습니다!
ENGRAVING SERVICE, LEATHER WATCH 230,000 WON
조각 서비스, 가죽 시계 230,000원
ENGRAVING SERVICE TO MY SON…
조각 서비스 내 아들에게…
TO MY SON WHOM I LOVE, JUNG-MIN
사랑하는 아들 정민에게
YOUR PURCHASE IS COMPLETE!
구매가 완료되었습니다!
Goodness.
선량.
MONEY FOR MY MOM, UNDERWEAR FOR MOTHER, TIE FOR MY HUSBAND
엄마를 위한 돈, 어머니를 위한 속옷, 남편을 위한 넥타이
ART BOOK FOR MY DAUGHTER, WATCH FOR MY SON
내 딸을 위한 아트북, 내 아들을 지켜주세요
I think it'd be correct to proceed with a laparotomy.
내 생각엔 그게 맞을 것 같아 개복수술을 진행합니다.
But I feel like a laparoscopy would be worth a shot too.
그런데 복강경을 받은 것 같은 느낌이 들어요 시도해 볼 가치도 있을 것입니다.
Laparoscopic surgery would be the best bet given his age.
복강경 수술 그의 나이를 고려하면 최선의 선택이 될 것입니다.
He'll recover faster, and there are lower chances
그 사람은 더 빨리 회복할 거예요. 그리고 확률도 낮고
of complications such as abdominal adhesions.
합병증의 복부 유착 등.
This patient is a particularly delicate case.
이 환자는 특히 민감한 경우입니다.
Of course that might be the case…
물론 그럴 수도 있겠네요...
Given the liver lesions,
간 병변을 고려하여,
a laparoscopic surgery would be pushing it.
복강경 수술 밀어붙일 것입니다.
If we do an RFA after the incision,
절개 후 RFA를 하면
we'll be able to get most of it.
우리는 그것의 대부분을 얻을 수 있을 것입니다.
So laparotomy would be the best.
그러니 개복수술이 최선일 것입니다.
It's metastasized through the liver and artery lymph nodes.
간을 통해 전이된 경우입니다. 및 동맥 림프절.
Shouldn't we remove the portions we are certain about
부분을 제거하면 안되는거 아닌가요? 우리는 확신한다
and then do chemotherapy before performing another surgery?
그리고 화학요법을 해라 다른 수술을 하기 전에?
We don't want to push things.
우리는 일을 추진하고 싶지 않습니다.
We all know the best course of action is to perform R0 resection
우리 모두는 최선의 행동 방침을 알고 있습니다. R0 절제술을 수행하는 것입니다
for patients who have colorectal cancer that has metastasized to the liver.
대장암 환자를 위한 간에 전이된 것입니다.
Administering a treatment when cancer cells are remaining
치료 관리 암세포가 남아있을 때
will cause the patient's state to worsen.
환자의 상태를 악화시키게 됩니다.
We must give the patient the best treatment
우리는 환자에게 최고의 치료
within the bounds of what the patient's condition allows.
범위 내에서 환자의 상태가 허용하는 것.
Isn't that what an oncologic surgeon should do?
그렇지 않나요? 종양외과 의사는 무엇을 해야 합니까?
I will judge whether I'm pushing things too far or not.
내가 밀어붙이고 있는지는 내가 판단할게 너무 멀든 아니든.
I hope this doesn't offend you,
이것이 당신을 화나게 하지 않기를 바랍니다.
but do you have the skill to remove all the metastasized cancer in the liver?
그런데 너한테 제거 기술이 있어? 간에 전이된 암은 모두?
I think you're being too daring.
내 생각엔 당신이 너무 대담한 것 같아요.
You're right.
당신 말이 맞아요.
I am a bit daring.
제가 좀 대담한 편이에요.
Because I am that competent.
내가 그만큼 유능하니까.
It's as if I'm watching Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon
마치 지켜보고 있는 것 같아 와호장룡, 숨은 용
-You can have a go at each other -Shall I?
-서로 쳐도 돼 -그럴까요?
Lift up the intestine.
내장을 들어 올리십시오.
Okay.
좋아요.
-Bring in the camera. -Okay.
-카메라를 가져오세요. -좋아요.
Turn the camera's angle to the left.
카메라 각도를 왼쪽으로 돌립니다.
Compared to the footage,
영상과 비교해보면,
the invasion into the sphincter isn't as deep.
침입하다 괄약근이 그렇게 깊지 않아요.
I think we can save the exterior.
내 생각엔 우리가 외관을 살릴 수 있을 것 같아.
We can preserve the anus by removing the sphincter.
항문을 보존할 수 있습니다 괄약근을 제거함으로써.
The patient will be so pleased.
환자는 매우 기뻐할 것입니다.
I know.
알아요.
We'll have to add a temporary stoma, but it can be removed in a few months.
임시 장루를 추가해야 합니다. 하지만 몇 달 안에 제거될 수 있습니다.
-Okay, I'll move downward now. -Okay.
-알겠습니다. 이제 아래로 이동하겠습니다. -좋아요.
SURGERY DURATION, ANESTHESIA DURATION
수술 기간, 마취 기간
-Provide suction for the fluid. -Yes, sir.
-유체에 대한 흡입력을 제공하십시오. - 네, 선생님.
This patient is famous.
이 환자는 유명해요.
If word gets around that you operated on him,
소문이 돌면 당신이 그 사람에게 수술을 했다는 것,
you'll get even busier.
당신은 더욱 바빠질 것이다.
Every patient is the same for me.
나에게는 모든 환자가 똑같다.
Scissors, please.
가위 주세요.
Why is he already waiting?
그 사람은 왜 벌써 기다리고 있는 걸까?
I would've called him when we were done.
우리가 끝나면 그 사람에게 전화했을 거에요.
Right?
오른쪽?
Things worked out so well, Chairman Oh.
일이 너무 잘됐어요, 오회장님.
I thought even your anus would have to be removed,
난 네 항문까지 생각했어 제거해야 할 것입니다,
but thankfully that wasn't necessary.
하지만 고맙게도 그럴 필요는 없었습니다.
Congratulations on being able to preserve your anus.
축하드립니다. 항문을 보존하기 위해.
Yes, it worked out well.
네, 잘 됐어요.
Of course.
물론.
Your quality of life changes drastically depending on if you have an anus or not.
삶의 질이 확연히 달라집니다 항문이 있는지 없는지에 따라.
The artificial stoma will only be in place while you undergo chemotherapy.
인공 장루는 제자리에 있어야만 합니다. 화학요법을 받는 동안.
What are you so happy about?
당신은 무엇 때문에 그렇게 행복합니까?
None of my children even care if I carry a poop bag around or not.
내 아이들 중 누구도 신경 쓰지 않아 내가 똥주머니를 가지고 다닐지 말지.
Goodness, no way.
맙소사, 절대 안돼.
They may not express it, but I bet they are feeling relieved.
표현하지 못할 수도 있지만, 하지만 그들은 안도감을 느끼고 있을 것 같아요.
And I…
그리고 나는…
bought this to give to you.
이것을 당신에게 주려고 샀습니다.
What is that?
저게 뭐에요?
Once you attach the stoma, you'll have to wear bigger underwear,
장루를 부착한 후, 더 큰 속옷을 입어야 해요.
so I bought this.
그래서 이걸 샀어요.
But since it's temporary, I'll get a refund for this.
하지만 일시적인 현상이기 때문에 이 금액은 환불해 드리겠습니다.
Why would you refund my gift?
왜 내 선물을 환불하려고 합니까?
-Give it to me. -It's big for you.
- 나에게 줘. - 너한테는 큰 일이야.
Goodness, all I have is money.
맙소사, 내가 가진 건 돈뿐이에요.
I'll have it tailored. Give it to me.
맞춤으로 해드립니다. 나에게 주세요.
-Really? -Give it to me.
-정말? - 나에게 줘.
-I'll open it for you. -Okay.
- 열어드릴게요. -좋아요.
-Do you want to see? -Sure.
-보고 싶니? -확신하는.
Goodness.
선량.
You regret being mean to me when we first met, don't you?
나한테 못되게 굴어서 후회하는구나 우리 처음 만났을 때, 그렇지?
But this isn't from the department store.
그러나 이것은 백화점에서 나온 것이 아닙니다.
-Just give it back. -No, it's fine.
- 그냥 돌려주세요. -아니요, 괜찮아요.
-I'll return-- -You already gave it to me.
-돌아갈게요-- -이미 나한테 줬잖아.
Going down.
내려갑니다.
The doors are closing.
문이 닫히고 있습니다.
You must be going home.
당신은 집에 가야합니다.
Yes.
예.
Going down.
내려갑니다.
The doors are closing.
문이 닫히고 있습니다.
PROFESSOR SEO IN-HO
서인호 교수
Dr. Moon.
문 박사.
Which way is your home?
당신의 집은 어느 방향인가요?
Have you gotten closer to your colleagues?
동료들과 좀 더 가까워졌나요?
It's still a bit awkward.
아직은 좀 어색해요.
Why?
왜?
Do you not get along?
사이좋게 지내지 못하시나요?
It's not that we don't get along,
우리가 사이가 안 좋은 건 아니지만,
but some bad rumors are going around the hospital.
하지만 나쁜 소문이 좀 있어 병원을 돌아다니고 있어요.
So it's making things awkward.
그래서 상황이 어색해지네요.
-Bad rumors? -You didn't hear?
-나쁜 소문이요? - 못 들었어?
They say Dr. Cha and GS Professor Seo are seeing each other.
차 박사님과 GS 서교수님이시더라구요 서로 만나고 있어요.
The whole hospital knows about the rumor.
그 소문은 병원 전체가 다 알고 있어요.
What are you talking about?
무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요?
It's just a rumor going around.
그냥 소문이 돌고 있는 것 뿐이에요.
When Dr. Cha fainted while she was administering CPR,
차 박사가 기절했을 때 그녀가 심폐소생술을 실시하는 동안,
Professor Seo ran over and worried about her--
서 교수가 달려왔다 그리고 그녀가 걱정되서--
Stop saying such nonsense!
그런 말도 안되는 소리는 그만둬!
They were just colleagues in med school.
그들은 단지 의과대학 동료들이었다.
Can't friends worry about each other?
친구들은 서로 걱정할 수 없나요?
And why are you going around and spreading rumors that haven't been confirmed?
그리고 왜 돌아다니면서 퍼뜨리는 거야? 확인되지 않은 소문이요?
Do you not have any loyalty to your colleagues?
당신은 없나요? 동료에 대한 충성심은 있습니까?
Take it. I don't need it.
가져가세요. 필요하지 않습니다.
What do you mean? What happened?
무슨 뜻이에요? 무슨 일이에요?
How can I go around wearing the same bracelet your wife has?
어떻게 입고 돌아다닐 수 있나요? 당신 아내가 가지고 있는 것과 같은 팔찌요?
How could you buy us the exact same bracelet?
어떻게 우리를 살 수 있었나요? 똑같은 팔찌야?
Seung-hi, calm down. Why don't we sit down first?
승희야, 진정해. 우리 먼저 앉는 게 어때요?
Jeong-suk found the receipt.
정숙은 영수증을 찾았다.
The receipt for the bracelet I gave you.
내가 준 팔찌 영수증.
I told her it was for her birthday, so I had no choice.
나는 그녀에게 그것이 그녀의 생일이라고 말했다. 그래서 나에게는 선택의 여지가 없었다.
Honestly, this is driving me crazy too!
솔직히 이것도 나를 미치게 만든다!
I'll make sure this never happens again.
다시는 이런 일이 발생하지 않도록 하겠습니다.
I'm really sorry.
정말 죄송해요.
Shall I get you another gift?
선물 하나 더 드릴까요?
He never says he's going to leave her.
그는 결코 그녀를 떠나겠다고 말하지 않습니다.
We got off early, so how about a latte?
우리 일찍 퇴근했는데 라떼 한잔 어때요?
Okay, let's go.
좋아, 가자.
Eun-seo.
은서.
Who is that?
그 사람은 누구입니까?
Your mom?
당신의 엄마?
Sorry, I have to go. Let's grab a latte together next time.
미안, 나 가야 해. 다음엔 같이 라떼 한잔하자.
I haven't picked you up in forever, right?
내가 영원히 당신을 데리러 온 건 아니죠?
How about we get something to eat?
우리 뭐 좀 먹을까?
-What do you want to eat? -Let's just go home.
-무엇을 먹고 싶어요? -그냥 집에 가자.
Without eating?
먹지 않고?
-Why? We can eat the sushi you-- -I said let's just go home!
-왜? 우리는 초밥을 먹을 수 있습니다-- -그냥 집에 가자고 했어!
Choi Eun-seo.
최은서.
Eun-seo.
은서.
What's wrong?
무슨 일이야?
Why are you so angry?
왜 그렇게 화가 났나요?
Get out.
나가세요.
You have to tell me what you're angry about to get over it.
나한테 말해줘야 해 당신이 화를 내는 이유는 무엇입니까?
You should find a nice guy and marry him.
좋은 남자 만나서 결혼해야지.
Where did that come from?
그거 어디서 나온 거야?
I have no plans to get a stepfather for you.
난 아무 계획도 없어 당신을 위해 의붓아버지를 구해 주려고요.
Why? Did that man tell you not to marry?
왜? 그 사람이 결혼하지 말라고 했나?
"That man"?
"그 사람"?
He's your dad, Eun-seo.
그 사람이 네 아빠, 은서야.
How can I call him "Dad" when I'm just his mistress' daughter?
어떻게 그를 "아빠"라고 부를 수 있나요? 내가 그 사람 여주인의 딸일 때?
What? Am I wrong?
무엇? 내가 틀렸나요?
It's true that you're his mistress!
당신이 그의 여주인이라는 것이 사실입니다!
Choi Eun-seo!
최은서!
If that's not true, why am I Choi Eun-seo?
그게 사실이 아니라면 나는 왜 최은서인가?
If I'm not just his mistress' daughter, why am I not Seo Eun-seo?
내가 그 사람 여주인의 딸이 아니라면, 나는 왜 서은서가 아닌가?
You're at an age where I don't have to explain every detail to you.
넌 내가 할 수 없는 나이야 당신에게 모든 세부 사항을 설명해야합니다.
Do you really want to hurt me like an immature teenager?
정말로 나에게 상처를 주고 싶은 거야? 철없는 십대 같나요?
Am I the only one who's hurting you?
당신에게 상처를 주는 사람은 나뿐인가요?
You're the one who had a kid with a married man!
당신이 바로 그 사람이에요 유부남과 아이를 낳은 사람!
You're the reason I can't ever call my dad "Dad"!
당신이 이유예요 난 절대 아빠를 '아빠'라고 부를 수 없어요!
Even if you get married and settle down,
결혼해서 안정을 취하더라도
a lot of things can change with time.
시간이 지나면 많은 것이 바뀔 수 있습니다.
Can't you just think of it that way?
그냥 그렇게 생각하면 안 되나요?
I can't understand it and I don't want to!
나는 그것을 이해할 수 없고 싶지도 않다!
Just…
그냥…
Just give me some time.
시간을 좀 주세요.
-It may be late, but I'll-- -But what?
-늦었지만 제가-- - 그런데 뭐?
Did he say he'll divorce his wife and come to you?
그 사람이 아내와 이혼하겠다고 했나요? 그리고 너한테 와?
Do you believe that?
당신은 그것을 믿습니까?
Even I can tell that's a plain lie.
나조차도 그것은 명백한 거짓말이라고 단언할 수 있다.
How can you be so naive at that age to believe all that?
그 나이에 어떻게 그렇게 순진할 수 있지? 그걸 다 믿으려고?
How long do I have to be the bad guy here?
나는 언제까지 여기서 나쁜 놈으로 남아 있어야 합니까?
You shouldn't have had me then.
그땐 날 갖지 말았어야 했어
You should've lived your life alone.
평생 혼자 살았어야 했는데.
Why did you have me
왜 나를 가졌나요?
just to get abandoned by your family and treated like this by your daughter?
단지 가족에게 버림받을 뿐 당신 딸한테도 이런 대우를 받았나요?
Because I wanted to meet you so badly.
너무 만나고 싶었기 때문이다.
I wanted to meet you so badly that I gave birth to you.
너무 만나고 싶었는데 내가 당신을 낳았다는 것입니다.
Because I wanted to meet you so much!
너무 만나고 싶었거든요!
GUSAN UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL
구산대학교병원
Yes, come in.
응, 들어와.
The meeting minutes?
회의록?
Yes. There's a seminar at half past seven on the fifth floor,
예. 세미나가 있어요 7시 반쯤 5층에서
and you'll have to come in and record the minutes.
그리고 넌 들어와야 해 그리고 분을 기록하세요.
Just come after work.
그냥 퇴근하고 오세요.
I see.
알겠어요.
Why? You don't want to do it?
왜? 당신은 그것을하고 싶지 않아?
Yes, I refuse.
예, 거절합니다.
Are there no other residents here?
여기에 다른 주민은 없나요?
Why are you asking me
왜 나한테 묻는 거야?
when I'm currently dispatched to a different department?
내가 지금 파견됐을 때 다른 부서로?
Furthermore…
게다가…
why are you suddenly speaking casually toward me?
갑자기 왜 그래? 나한테 아무렇지도 않게 말하는 거야?
You don't want to do it?
당신은 그것을하고 싶지 않아?
Of course not. I'll do it.
물론 그렇지 않습니다. 내가 할게요.
Go to the in-house library and get these materials for me.
사내 도서관으로 이동 그리고 나에게 이 자료를 가져다 주세요.
Please organize these materials.
이 자료들을 정리해주세요.
Make a presentation for tomorrow morning's meeting.
프레젠테이션 만들기 내일 아침 회의를 위해.
Can you type up this thesis?
이 논문을 타이핑할 수 있나요?
My wrists aren't in good shape.
손목 상태가 좋지 않습니다.
Can you type faster?
더 빨리 입력할 수 있나요?
You're so slow.
당신은 너무 느리다.
Hello.
안녕하세요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Have I gotten a lot worse?
내 상태가 많이 나빠졌나요?
As expected, your LFT has elevated slightly.
예상대로, LFT가 약간 상승했습니다.
You are taking your immunosuppressants regularly, right?
당신은 복용하고 있습니다 면역억제제를 정기적으로 맞죠?
Yes.
예.
To be honest, I sometimes forget because I'm so busy.
솔직히 말해서 가끔 잊어버릴 때도 있어 왜냐하면 나는 너무 바쁘기 때문이다.
No matter how busy you are,
아무리 바빠도
you can't forget to take them and need to take them on time.
잊지 말고 가져가세요 그리고 제 시간에 맞춰서 가져가야 해요.
Doing that once or twice won't do much harm.
그거 한 번 해보면 아니면 두 번은 큰 해를 끼치 지 않을 것입니다.
But in the worst-case scenario, your liver could get damaged again.
하지만 최악의 상황에서는 간이 다시 손상될 수 있습니다.
You can't slack off just because you feel all right now.
느슨해지면 안돼 지금은 괜찮다고 느끼기 때문이에요.
I don't know if it's right to say not to work too hard,
맞는지 모르겠어요 너무 열심히 일하지 말라고,
but your health has to take priority.
하지만 건강이 우선시 되어야 합니다.
Always remember this.
항상 이것을 기억하십시오.
"My liver is precious."
"내 간은 소중해요."
ANNEX SURGERY ROOM
별관 수술실
Why not send the dispatched residents from family medicine to my department?
파견주민은 왜 보내지 않는가? 가정의학과에서 내 진료과로?
I don't know about that.
나는 그것에 대해 모른다.
The family medicine doctors don't seem to prefer working in your department.
가정의학 의사들은 아닌 것 같아요 당신 부서에서 일하는 것을 선호합니다.
For primary care, they need to learn about the stomach and intestines,
일차 진료를 위해서는 다음을 배워야 합니다. 위와 장에 대해서
I don't know if they'll have the time to go to you.
그들이 그럴지는 모르겠지만 당신에게 갈 시간입니다.
Family medicine doctors should know about hepatobiliary and pancreatic conditions
가정의학과 의사가 알아야 할 사항 간담도 및 췌장 질환
like acute cholecystitis and pancreatitis.
급성 담낭염이나 췌장염과 같습니다.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I'm short on hands too.
나도 손이 부족해요.
Gosh, you startled me!
맙소사, 너 때문에 놀랐어!
Goodness, Dr. Jeon.
맙소사, 전 박사님.
Why are you so shocked?
왜 그렇게 충격을 받았나요?
I mean, how could I not get shocked when you're standing there like a ghost?
내 말은, 내가 어떻게 충격을 받지 않을 수 있단 말인가? 유령처럼 거기 서 있을 때?
I was just seeing if you were giving out the wrong order.
방금 보고 있었어 당신이 잘못된 명령을 내린 경우.
Your eyes were half-closed.
당신의 눈은 반쯤 감겨 있었습니다.
I was focused and entered everything in perfectly.
나는 집중했다 모든 것을 완벽하게 입력했습니다.
I have one thing to ask you.
한 가지 물어볼 것이 있습니다.
To ask me?
나한테 물어보려고?
What's going on between you and Professor Seo?
무슨 일이야? 당신과 서교수 사이에?
What do you mean?
무슨 뜻이에요?
There are rumors about you two being a couple.
소문이 있다 너희 둘이 커플이라는 얘기.
Someone asked me, but I couldn't refute it since I don't know the details.
누군가 나에게 물었지만 나는 반박할 수 없었다. 자세한 내용은 모르기 때문에.
Since it's a bother to be continually asked this,
귀찮으니까 계속해서 이런 질문을 받는데,
will you just be straight with me and tell me if it's a yes or a no?
그냥 나한테 솔직하게 말해줄래? 그리고 그것이 예인지 아니오인지 말해주세요.
Nothing is going on between us.
우리 사이에는 아무 일도 일어나지 않습니다.
You're getting excessively worked up for it to be nothing.
당신은 지나치게 흥분하고 있습니다 아무것도 아니기 때문에.
I'll let it go for now.
지금은 그대로 두겠습니다.
"Seeing each other"?
"서로 만나다"?
Yes.
예.
Professor Seo and Dr. Cha.
서 교수와 차 박사.
Does that lady have some kind of irresistible charm I don't know about?
그 아줌마한테 그런 게 있어? 내가 모르는 거부할 수 없는 매력이 있다고?
Why do men swarm around her?
왜 남자들은 그녀 주위에 모여들까?
She seems close to Professor Roy too.
그녀는 로이 교수와도 가까운 것 같습니다.
You always talk about her too.
당신도 항상 그녀에 대해 이야기합니다.
Why is everybody so eager to get involved with her?
왜 다들 그렇게 열심이지? 그녀와 관계를 맺으려고?
Damn it.
젠장.
Focus.
집중하다.
This is about your father.
이것은 당신의 아버지에 관한 것입니다.
-It's just a rumor. -How would you know?
-그냥 소문일 뿐이에요. - 어떻게 알겠어요?
Darn you.
젠장.
Keep a close eye on the professor.
교수님을 잘 관찰하세요.
Normally I shouldn't be doing this, but I'm having trouble standing.
평소라면 이러면 안 되는데, 하지만 서 있기가 힘들어요.
A colleague of mine will come within an hour.
내 동료 한 시간 안에 올 거예요.
Can I ask you to watch over her until then?
물어봐도 될까요? 그때까지 그녀를 지켜주려고?
Okay, it's a simple test so it won't take too long.
좋아, 간단한 테스트야 그러면 너무 오래 걸리지 않을 거예요.
But the patient has a wound on her wrist.
그런데 환자의 손목에 상처가 있습니다.
Is there a way to slightly loosen the handcuffs?
살짝 풀 수 있는 방법 없을까요? 수갑?
Okay, we'll be back soon.
좋아요, 곧 돌아올게요.
Today we're going to take an X-ray and do an ECG.
오늘 우리는 갈거야 엑스레이를 찍고 ECG를 찍으러 갑니다.
These are simple tests, so you don't have to worry.
간단한 테스트들인데, 그러니 걱정할 필요가 없습니다.
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
-Are you free? -I need to run some tests.
- 시간 있어요? -몇 가지 테스트를 실행해야 합니다.
Go to Gangnam Hospital right away.
당장 강남병원으로 가세요.
My research materials are there, and I need you to get them.
내 연구자료가 거기 있는데, 그리고 당신이 그걸 구해 줘야 해요.
I'll give you a contact so you can get the materials.
연락처 드릴께요 그래야 재료를 얻을 수 있어요.
But--
하지만--
One second.
1초.
Excuse me, Dr. Choi.
죄송합니다, 최 박사님.
Can I go in one hour?
한 시간 안에 갈 수 있나요?
I have to be with the patient for her tests.
나는 그래야만 한다 검사를 위해 환자와 함께.
Since when do residents go and oversee a patient's tests?
주민들은 언제부터 가서 환자의 검사를 감독한다고요?
The thing is…
문제는…
-Say goodbye. -Bye.
- 작별 인사를 하세요. -안녕.
Get an intern to take care of the patient's tests and go.
돌봐줄 인턴을 구하세요 환자의 검사를 받고 가십시오.
Ma'am, are you all right?
부인, 괜찮으세요?
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
You must be staying at Gusan University Hospital.
당신은 머물고 있어야합니다 구산대학교병원에서.
Excuse me, I'm sorry to ask this of a stranger,
실례합니다, 미안해요 낯선 사람에게 이런 걸 물어보면
but can you lend me some money for a taxi?
그런데 택시비 좀 빌려주실 수 있나요?
-What do I do? -What's wrong?
- 어떻게 해야 하나요? - 무슨 일이야?
Ms. Jang Hae-nam disappeared.
장해남씨가 사라졌다.
You haven't found Ms. Jang Hae-nam?
장해남 씨를 아직 못 찾으셨나요?
No.
아니요.
Are you out of your mind?
정신이 나갔나요?
-I'm sorry. -Shut up!
-죄송합니다. -입 다물어!
How dare an incompetent resident like you humiliate our hospital?
무능한 주민이 어떻게 감히 당신이 우리 병원을 모욕하는 것처럼요?
There's a bed but no patient!
침대는 있는데 환자가 없어요!
Damn it!
젠장!
Wait in the medical office.
진료실에서 기다리세요.
Where are you heading?
어디로 가고 있나요?
To Gupabal.
구파발에게.
Where in Gupabal?
구파발은 어디인가요?
Gupabal.
구파발.
Well…
음…
I'm not sure if it's still there.
아직도 거기에 있는지 잘 모르겠습니다.
What was the name of that church?
그 교회 이름이 뭐였나요?
Goodness, I can't seem to remember it.
맙소사, 기억이 나지 않는 것 같아요.
Ma'am.
부인.
Do you know your home phone number?
집 전화번호를 아시나요?
Home phone number?
집 전화번호는요?
Do you know the cell phone number of any of your family members?
휴대폰 번호를 아시나요? 당신의 가족 중에 누구라도 있나요?
Your kids.
당신의 아이들.
I have a daughter.
나에겐 딸이 있다.
I want to see her
나는 그녀를보고 싶다
just once…
딱 한 번만…
before I die.
내가 죽기 전에.
Dr. Cha!
차 박사님!
They found her?
그들이 그녀를 찾았나요?
The police station called. A taxi driver brought her to the police.
경찰서에서 전화가 왔습니다. 택시 운전사가 그녀를 경찰에 데려갔습니다.
She was speaking incoherently so the driver thought she had dementia.
그녀는 일관되지 않은 말을 하고 있었다 그래서 운전자는 치매에 걸린 줄 알았어요.
Is she all right?
그녀는 괜찮나요?
Yes, you don't have to worry.
네, 걱정하지 마세요.
It worked out.
성공했습니다.
That's such a relief.
정말 다행이네요.
It's such a relief.
정말 안심이 됩니다.
CHIEF LIM JONG-KWON
임종권 실장
Do you think you can continue to work?
계속 일할 수 있을 것 같나요?
What?
무엇?
Honestly, I've had a lot of worries ever since you came here.
솔직히 고민이 많았어요 당신이 여기 온 이후로.
It's possible to cover up any trouble you cause within this department.
어떤 트러블도 커버 가능해요 당신은 이 부서 내에서 원인을 제공합니다.
But nothing can be done about the trouble you cause
하지만 아무것도 할 수 없어 당신이 일으킨 문제에 대해
in another department.
다른 부서에서.
-I'm sorry-- -That's why we avoid old residents.
-미안해요-- -그래서 우리는 노인들을 피합니다.
If someone young makes a mistake, it's just a mistake.
어린 사람이 실수를 하면 그것은 단지 실수입니다.
But if someone older makes a mistake,
하지만 나이 많은 사람이 실수를 하면
it's incompetence.
무능력입니다.
If your livelihood isn't at stake,
생계가 위태롭지 않다면,
perhaps you could reconsider your position here.
아마도 당신은 다시 생각해 볼 수 있을 것입니다 여기 당신의 위치.
Do you mean I should quit?
내가 그만둬야 한다는 뜻인가요?
Did it sound like I meant that?
내 말이 그런 뜻으로 들렸나요?
I just meant you should give it some thought.
난 그냥 네가 그래야 한다고 말한 거야 좀 생각해 보세요.
Professor, it's my fault that the patient escaped due to my carelessness.
교수님, 환자가 잘못한 건 제 잘못이에요 내 부주의로 인해 탈출했다.
I have no excuses to give on that matter.
나는 그 문제에 대해 변명의 여지가 없습니다.
But I find it unfair that a mistake is equated
하지만 나는 그것이 불공평하다고 생각한다. 실수는 동일하다
to incompetence just because I'm older.
단지 나이가 많다는 이유로 무능력해지는 것.
I'm still just a first-year resident who has a lot to learn.
난 아직 1년차 레지던트야 배울 점이 많은 사람.
Are you going home?
집에 가시나요?
Yes.
예.
How are you getting home?
집에 어떻게 가나요?
I feel like I've become useless.
내가 쓸모없어진 것 같은 느낌이 든다.
I'm such an idiot at the hospital.
나는 병원에서 정말 바보입니다.
My body isn't the same as before.
내 몸이 예전과 같지 않네요.
And I've neglected my daughter who's trying to get into college.
그리고 난 내 딸을 무시했어요 대학에 가려고 하는 사람.
Is it right for me to continue doing this?
내가 이 일을 계속하는 것이 옳은가?
Then just quit.
그럼 그냥 그만 두세요.
Even easy tasks feel hard if you haven't done them in 20 years.
쉬운 일이라도 어렵게 느껴진다 20년 동안 안 했다면.
Not to mention the work doctors do.
의사가 하는 일은 말할 것도 없고요.
That's true.
그것은 사실이다.
If you're not confident, you should just quit sooner than later.
자신감이 없다면, 그냥 빨리 그만둬야 할 것 같아요.
You won't learn anything at the hospital with that attitude.
병원에서는 아무것도 배울 수 없습니다 그런 태도로.
I have plans, so I'll take a taxi from here.
나에겐 계획이 있어요. 그럼 여기서 택시를 탈게요.
It's a relief you're healthy and being discharged.
건강하시다니 다행이네요 그리고 퇴원.
I still have to undergo chemotherapy.
아직 항암치료를 받아야 해요.
Don't be discouraged just because you're older.
낙담하지 마세요 단지 당신이 나이가 많기 때문입니다.
Make sure to learn a lot and become a great doctor.
꼭 많이 배워보세요 그리고 훌륭한 의사가 되세요.
When you start your own practice, I'll be your patient.
혼자 연습을 시작하면, 나는 당신의 환자가 될 것입니다.
Just imagining it makes me happy.
상상만 해도 행복해집니다.
Why leave it just as an imagination?
왜 상상으로만 남겨두나요?
You can make it a reality.
당신은 그것을 현실로 만들 수 있습니다.
But why do you look so sad? Did something bad happen?
그런데 왜 그렇게 슬픈 표정을 짓고 있나요? 뭔가 나쁜 일이 있었나요?
Do I look sad?
내가 슬퍼 보여?
Gosh.
이런.
I'm sorry. I'm being silly.
죄송합니다. 나는 바보 같은 짓을 하고 있다.
Don't be like that and come sit here.
그러지 말고 여기로 와서 앉으세요.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
What's wrong? Tell me everything.
무슨 일이야? 나에게 모든 것을 말해주세요.
Once you let everything out, you'll feel better.
일단 모든 것을 털어놓고 나면, 기분이 좋아질 거예요.
I'm afraid…
나는 두려워한다…
I'll have to quit working at the hospital.
병원 일을 그만둬야겠습니다.
Why?
왜?
Because I'm lacking in so many ways,
나는 여러모로 부족하기 때문에
and I'm foolish.
그리고 나는 어리석다.
You're literally blinded by your own privilege.
당신은 말 그대로 눈이 멀었습니다. 당신의 특권으로.
You should be thankful for this chance at your age.
감사해야 해 네 나이에 이 기회를 위해.
What kind of gibberish are you saying?
무슨 횡설수설을 말하는 거야?
Stop saying such useless things and think about learning and improving.
그런 쓸데없는 소리는 그만둬 배우고 개선하는 것에 대해 생각하십시오.
You should learn by taking things one step at a time
물건을 가져가서 배워야 해 한 번에 한 걸음씩
and become a great doctor.
그리고 훌륭한 의사가 되세요.
Why are you laughing?
왜 웃어요?
I'm being serious right now.
나 지금 진지하게 말하는 중이야.
You sound like my father.
당신은 내 아버지처럼 들립니다.
If my father were still alive,
내 아버지가 아직 살아 계셨다면,
I think he would scold me just like you did.
내 생각엔 그 사람이 나를 꾸짖을 것 같아 당신이 그랬던 것처럼요.
But…
하지만…
later on…
나중에…
he would say,
그는 이렇게 말할 것이다.
"Fine, do whatever you want."
"좋아, 하고 싶은 대로 해라."
So?
그래서?
Are you just going to quit?
그냥 그만 두실 건가요?
Why would you come to my office when you can talk to me at home?
왜 내 사무실에 오려고 합니까? 집에서 언제 나랑 얘기할 수 있어?
Do you know there's a rumor about us that something is going on
우리에 대한 소문이 있다는 걸 아시나요? 뭔가 일어나고 있는 것 같아
between us?
우리 사이?
I know.
알아요.
You know?
알잖아?
Yes, I know.
네, 알아요.
That's it? Nothing else comes to mind?
그게 다야? 더 이상 떠오르는 게 없나요?
You said your husband is dead so it might not hurt you,
남편이 죽었다고 하더군요 그럼 너한테 상처 안 줄 수도 있겠지.
but I'm an officially married man.
하지만 저는 정식으로 결혼한 남자예요.
How will I be able to face my patients
나는 환자들을 어떻게 대할 것인가?
when I'm labeled as some sordid cheater?
내가 더러운 사기꾼으로 낙인찍혔을 때?
Do you only care about your professional achievements?
너만 신경쓰냐? 당신의 직업적 성취에 대해?
Do you not care if your husband and son's reputations are destroyed?
남편이 상관없나요? 아들의 명예가 무너졌나요?
Were you always this selfish?
당신은 항상 이렇게 이기적이었나요?
I'm going to quit the hospital.
병원을 그만 두겠습니다.
What--
뭐--
Does that make you feel better?
그러면 기분이 좋아지나요?
Why do you have to put it that way?
왜 그렇게 넣어야합니까?
Why did you suddenly change your mind?
왜 갑자기 마음이 바뀌었나요?
It's not sudden.
갑작스러운 일이 아닙니다.
I only prepared for the resident exam.
레지던트 시험만 준비했어요.
I make mistakes all the time at the hospital.
나는 실수를 한다 병원에서 항상.
And my health isn't great.
그리고 건강도 좋지 않아요.
More importantly, I need to help I-rang with her college admissions.
무엇보다 아이랑을 도와줘야 해 그녀의 대학 입학과 함께.
They say your kids are the scariest people you'll meet.
그들은 당신의 아이들이라고 말합니다 당신이 만날 가장 무서운 사람들은 바로 당신입니다.
What will I do if she blames me if she doesn't get into college?
그녀가 나를 비난하면 나는 어떻게 할 것인가? 만약 그 사람이 대학에 들어가지 못한다면?
Right.
오른쪽.
That's a good idea.
좋은 생각이에요.
When will you tell the hospital?
병원에는 언제 말해줄 거예요?
In a few days.
며칠 안에.
I need some time to sort things out.
정리할 시간이 좀 필요해요.
I don't want to cause trouble to the department I've been dispatched to.
문제를 일으키고 싶지 않아요 내가 파견된 부서로.
I was sent here because the resident before me quit.
나는 여기로 보내졌다 나보다 먼저 온 주민이 그만뒀기 때문이다.
So how can I just quit too?
그럼 나도 그만둘 수는 없을까?
You don't have to worry about that. What you think matters most.
그것에 대해 걱정할 필요가 없습니다. 당신이 가장 중요하다고 생각하는 것.
Will they allow me to take a one-year break?
그들이 나를 허락할까? 1년 쉬려고?
Don't worry.
괜찮아요.
If they don't accept you next year, I'll pull some strings
만약 내년에 당신을 받아들이지 않는다면, 끈을 좀 당겨볼게
and find you a spot in another hospital.
그리고 다른 병원에 자리를 찾아보세요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
She's going to quit?
그 사람이 그만둘 건가요?
I'm sure of it.
나는 그것을 확신한다.
You must have had a hard time.
힘든 시간을 보내셨을 텐데요.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Her quitting takes care of one of my worries.
그녀의 그만두는 것은 중요하다 내 걱정 중 하나야.
Will I see you in the conference room? I heard there's some sort of event.
회의실에서 볼까요? 뭔가 이벤트가 있다고 들었어요.
I heard about it.
나는 그것에 대해 들었습니다.
-If I have time, I'll go. -Okay.
-시간이 있으면 가겠습니다. -좋아요.
Let's see each other if we can.
가능하다면 서로 만나자.
This looks so delicious.
정말 맛있어 보이네요.
Do you even have time to make it at home?
집에서 만들 시간이 있나요?
-I should have made it for you. -No need.
-내가 당신을 위해 만들어 줬어야 했는데. - 필요없어요.
Mom.
엄마.
I am…
나는…
going to quit the hospital.
병원을 그만 두려고요.
What?
무엇?
Why?
왜?
Is it too hard for you to continue?
계속하기가 너무 어렵나요?
Yes, and also…
응, 그리고…
I-rang is in 12th grade,
아이랑은 12학년이고,
and she's having trouble since I'm not there to help her.
그리고 그 사람은 문제를 겪고 있어 내가 그 사람을 도와주러 거기 있는 게 아니거든요.
I see.
알겠어요.
I'm sure you've thought this through.
나는 당신이 이것을 깊이 생각했다고 확신합니다.
Don't be disappointed.
실망하지 마십시오.
Your health is the top priority,
고객님의 건강이 최우선이며,
and they say kids are more precious than any treasure.
아이들이 더 소중하다고 하잖아요 어떤 보물보다
There's nothing more precious in the world.
아무것도 없어요 세상에서 더 소중한 것.
I didn't expect you to react like this.
당신이 이런 반응을 보일 줄은 몰랐어요.
I thought you'd be more upset than me.
나보다 당신이 더 속상할 거라 생각했어요.
That's because you were so young back then.
그 이유는 그땐 너 너무 어렸잖아.
And it was obvious your mother-in-law would harass you.
그리고 그것은 분명했다 시어머니가 당신을 괴롭힐 것입니다.
But you were able to raise Jung-min and I-rang until now.
하지만 넌 키울 수 있었어 지금까지 정민과 아이랑.
If you think about that, there's nothing to be disappointed or upset about.
생각해보면 별거 아닌데 실망하거나 화를 내는 것.
Right.
오른쪽.
You're right.
당신 말이 맞아요.
What you say is always right.
당신이 말하는 것은 항상 옳습니다.
I made an appointment for your checkup at this hospital.
약속을 잡았어요 이 병원에서 검진을 받으시려면
That's the least I can do for you before I quit.
그게 최소한이야 내가 그만두기 전에 당신을 위해 할 수 있어요.
You're so stubborn! I told you there's no need for that!
당신은 너무 고집스러워요! 그럴 필요 없다고 말했잖아!
Goodness, Mom. You're the one that's stubborn.
맙소사, 엄마. 당신은 고집이 센 사람입니다.
I'm not going to do it!
난 안 할 거야!
No, just do it.
아니요, 그냥 하세요.
No.
아니요.
Come on!
어서!
Goodness.
선량.
Dr. Cha, what brings you here?
차 박사님, 무슨 일로 여기까지 오셨나요?
You've already heard?
이미 들었나요?
No, it's not that.
아니요, 그게 아닙니다.
I just had something to tell you.
방금 당신에게 할 말이 있었어요.
It's a good thing you came. What perfect timing.
오셨다니 다행이네요. 정말 완벽한 타이밍입니다.
The hospital director wants to see you. Come with me.
병원 원장이 당신을 만나고 싶어합니다. 나와 함께 가자.
The hospital director?
병원장?
Hello.
안녕하세요.
I've lived 76 years,
나는 76년을 살았다.
but I lived as a miser who didn't even spend 100 won on others.
하지만 난 구두쇠로 살았어 남에게 100원도 안 쓴 사람.
Even I am moved by the fact that I am donating not 100 won
나조차도 그 사실에 감동을 받는다. 내가 100원도 안 기부한다고
or one million won,
아니면 100만원,
but ten billion won.
하지만 100억 원.
I would first like to sincerely thank Professor Seo In-ho
나는 먼저 좋겠다 서인호 교수님 진심으로 감사드립니다
and Professor Roy Kim for operating on me.
그리고 수술해주신 로이킴 교수님.
10 BILLION WON DONATION CEREMONY
100억 기부식
But there is another doctor who helped give me this new life.
그런데 다른 의사가 있어요. 나에게 새로운 삶을 살도록 도와준 사람.
And that
그리고 그
is Dr. Cha Jeong-suk.
차정숙 박사입니다.
Dr. Cha Jeong-suk, please come up to the stage.
차정숙 박사님, 무대 위로 올라와 주세요.
Come up here.
여기로 올라오세요.
While others treated me kindly on the outside
다른 사람들이 나를 대하는 동안 밖에서는 친절하게
and treated me with contempt inside for being a cranky old man,
그리고 속으로는 나를 경멸했다 까칠한 노인이라서,
Dr. Cha Jeong-suk was different.
차정숙 박사는 달랐다.
When I broke down and cried due to my condition,
내가 무너졌을 때 내 상태 때문에 울었고,
she treated me sincerely and comforted me.
그녀는 나를 진심으로 대하고 위로해주었다.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
And when my heart stopped, she gave it her all to save me.
그리고 내 심장이 멈췄을 때, 그녀는 나를 구하기 위해 모든 것을 바쳤습니다.
After she found out I didn't have to use a permanent stoma bag after surgery,
그녀가 내가 사용할 필요가 없다는 것을 알게 된 후 수술 후 영구 장루 주머니,
she was happier for me
그 사람은 나 때문에 더 행복해졌어
than even my own kids.
심지어 내 아이들보다.
She had unconditional compassion for me.
그녀는 나에게 무조건적인 연민을 갖고 있었습니다.
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
Thank you so much.
매우 감사합니다.
I won't forget this until I die.
나는 죽을 때까지 이것을 잊지 않을 것이다.
I'm not sure if it's because the work is hard,
잘 모르겠어요 일이 힘들다면,
but Dr. Cha said that she might quit.
그런데 차 박사님이 그만둘 수도 있다고 하더군요.
But I will keep my eyes peeled for you all.
하지만 난 계속할 거야 내 눈은 당신 모두를 위해 벗겨졌습니다.
If you let this kind of talent get away, this hospital has no future.
이런 인재를 그냥 놔두면 이 병원에는 미래가 없습니다.
And I'm going to take back every single bit of my ten billion won.
그리고 난 다시 가져갈 거야 내 백억 원 한 푼도.
I am going to continuously storm in here
난 여기 계속해서 돌진할 거야
and check until Dr. Cha Jeong-suk becomes a specialist.
차정숙 박사님까지 확인해보세요 전문가가 됩니다.
Actually, it would even be better if she became a professor here.
사실 그게 더 나을텐데 그녀가 여기서 교수가 된다면요.
If Dr. Cha wants to do research,
차박사가 연구를 하고 싶다면,
I will fund it all, no questions asked!
나는 모든 자금을 지원할 것입니다. 질문은 없습니다!
DONATION AGREEMENT FOR HOSPITAL DEVELOPMENT FUND
기부 계약 병원 발전 기금
OH CHANG-GYU
오창규
10 BILLION WON DONATION CEREMONY
100억 기부식
CHAIRMAN OH CHANG-GYU, GUSAN UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL
오창규 회장님, 구산대학교병원
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
Professor Seo, you too.
서교수님도요.
All right.
괜찮은.
In honor of Dr. Cha Jeong-suk,
차정숙 박사님을 기리며,
please give another round of applause.
다시한번 박수 부탁드립니다.
He's going to buy us two robotic surgical systems.
그 사람이 우리를 사려고 해요 두 개의 로봇 수술 시스템.
She's our lucky charm.
그녀는 우리의 행운의 부적입니다.
I knew it from the first time I saw her.
나는 그녀를 처음 봤을 때부터 그것을 알고 있었다.
-Take good care of her. -I will.
- 그녀를 잘 돌봐주세요. -그럴게요.
Professor Seo, you must be happy.
서교수님, 행복하시겠어요.
Yes.
예.
Excuse me, I'll get going first.
죄송해요, 제가 먼저 가볼게요.
Okay.
좋아요.
You get involved in everything.
당신은 모든 일에 참여합니다.
Dr. Cha.
차 박사.
Are you really going to quit?
정말 그만둘 건가요?
Are you crazy?
제정신이에요?
A murderer escaped the hospital without authorization.
살인자가 병원에서 탈출했습니다 승인 없이.
I don't think this is something to be taken lightly.
내 생각엔 이건 아닌 것 같아 가볍게 여겨야 할 일.
Why are you so keen on kicking me out?
왜 그렇게 날 쫓아내려고 하는 거야?
How about you stop deceiving your wife?
이제 그만 아내를 속이는 게 어때요?
You and Professor Choi Seung-hi.
당신과 최승희 교수님.
I think maybe that guy is interested in you.
아마 그럴 것 같아요 그 사람이 당신에게 관심이 있어요.
No matter what happens, you need to stay strong.
무슨 일이 있어도 당신은 강한 상태를 유지해야합니다.
-What brings you here? -I have something to tell you.
-무슨 일로 여기까지 오셨나요? - 드릴 말씀이 있습니다.
Subtitle translation by: Yoon-ji Chi
자막번역 : 지윤지